<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [

  <!ENTITY dhfirstname "<firstname>Petr</firstname>">
  <!ENTITY dhsurname   "<surname>Kubanek</surname>">
  <!ENTITY dhdate      "<date>2012-03-25</date>">
  <!ENTITY dhsection   "<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>">
  <!ENTITY dhemail     "<email>petr@kubanek.net</email>">
  <!ENTITY dhusername  "Petr Kubanek">
  <!ENTITY dhpackage   "rts2-mon">

  <!ENTITY % rts2 SYSTEM "rts2.ent">
  %rts2;
]>

<refentry>
  <refentryinfo>
    <title>&dhpackage;</title>
    <productname>rts2</productname>
    <productnumber>&rts2version;</productnumber>
    &dhdate;
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        &dhfirstname;
        &dhsurname;
	<contrib>Wrote most of the RTS2 package.</contrib>
	<address>
          &dhemail;
	</address>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <copyright>
      <year>2007,2010</year>
      <holder>&dhusername;</holder>
    </copyright>
    &legal;
  </refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>&dhpackage;</refentrytitle>
    &dhsection;
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>&dhpackage;</refname>
    <refpurpose>Allow interactive control of the RTS2 system.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <cmdsynopsis>
      <command>&dhpackage;</command>
      <arg choice="opt"><option>--command <replaceable>device</replaceable>.<replaceable>command</replaceable></option></arg>
      <arg choice="opt"><option>-r <replaceable>refresh rate</replaceable></option></arg>
      <arg choice="opt"><option>-c</option></arg>
      &clientapp;
    </cmdsynopsis>

    &helpsynopsis;

  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsect1 id="description">
    <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
    <para>
      <command>rts2-mon</command> is n-curses based tool for manipulating
      devices available in RTS2 system. You can read and modify variables of
      every device connected to the system. It allows fully interactive work with the system.
    </para>
    <para>
      You cannot take images with <command>rts2-mon</command>. To take images,
      please see <command>rts2-focusc</command>,
      <command>rts2-xfocusc</command> or <command>rts2-scriptexec</command>
      commands. To take images autonomously, use either
      <command>rts2-executor</command> or <command>rts2-scriptor</command>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Please read at least the <link linkend="variables">variables format</link>
      section, to understand how the arrays are displayed.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="basic_operation">
    <title>BASIC OPERATION</title>
    <para>
      To leave <command>rts2-mon</command>, use F10 or ctrl+c combination.
    </para>

    <para>
      Probably the most basic operation is to switch system states. Please
      press F2, F3, or F4 keys to switch states. To switch system to on, you
      will press F4. When system is in on, it is observing.
    </para>

    <para>
      To switch system to off, please press F2 key. To switch to standby, use
      F3 keys. Use off state when you are sure you will not observe, or use F3
      key and standby mode when you think you might be able to observe later
      tonight.
    </para>

    <para>
      After you press key to change state, small confirmation window will
      appear. Use left and right keys and enter key to confirm your selection.
      You most probably would like to press enter key to confirm selected yes.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can also change various values. Use keys (up and down), tabulator key
      to select a value. Writable values are marked with W in front of the value
      name. You can only change writable values. Once you highlight value, hit
      enter key to change it. Confirm the change with enter, or cancel it with
      ESC key.
    </para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>RTS2-MON SCREEN</title>

    <para>
      When you run <command>rts2-mon</command>, screen is divided into four principal
      areas - menu bar, device list and status display, RTS2 messages
      space and status bar at bottom.
    </para>

    <para>
      Standart screen layout will display following elements:

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>menu</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This is the uppermost line of the screen. You can enter menu
	      pressing F9 key, and exit it pressing ESC key. In menu you will
	      find generic command to switch RTS2 to off, standby and on
	      states.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>device listing</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Devices are listed in left part of the screen. You can use up and
	      down arrows to move between devices. Once you have selected
	      device which you want, press TAB key to move to the variable
	      listing.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>variable list</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The center and right part of the screen holds information about
	      RTS2 device variables, or device states. For central server, list
	      of devices and their states will be shown. "status" shows state
	      of all available devices.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      Variables which can be changed have W (for Writable) before their
	      name. Selecting them with movement keys and pressing enter (or
	      F6) shows a dialog box, where user can edit their value.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      Variables which will be recorded to FITS headers of acquired
	      files are on color terminals show in blue color. Variables which
	      will not be recorded are show in black.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>log window</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Log window display messages, as they are passed through RTS2
	      system. Those messages include debug messages. To change filter
	      which governs which message will be displayed, go to the menu and
	      select "Debug" option.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>status bar</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Status bar display current system status. Left is system state
	      (on, standby or off and substate - day, night, etc..), right is
	      current <acronym>UT</acronym>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="keys">
    <title>KEYS</title>

     <refsect2>
      <title>State switching keys</title>
    
      <para>
	RTS2 state can be switched by F2, F3 and F4 keys. After you press that
	key, message dialog with question to confirm state change appear. You
	can use arrow keys to change answer, and confirm the message box by
	pressing enter. If you choose Yes as answer to question, RTS2 state
	will be changed.
      </para>

      <para>
	For detailed discussions of various states, please see
	<citerefentry><refentrytitle>rts2</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7</manvolnum></citerefentry>.
      </para>

      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>F2</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Switch RTS2 to off state.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>F3</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Switch RTS2 to standby state.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>F4</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Switch RTS2 to on state.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Movement keys</title>

      <para>
        As text which should be displayed in <command>rts2-mon</command> windows must
        not necessary fit inside windows where it should be
	displayed, following keys can be used to shift text.
      </para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>up</option>
	    <option>down</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Move focus on selection list up or down.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>home</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Move focus on selection list to first entry.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>end</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Move focus on selection list to last entry.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>left, right (arrows)</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Shift text left or right, so part which cannot be visible becomes visible.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>tab</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Moves active window. Active window is marked with black window
	      border. You can switch between devices, values and log area.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>rts2-mon functions keys</title>
    
      <para>
	Those are keys, which execute <command>rts2-mon</command> functions.
      </para>

      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>F5</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Refresh display.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>Enter</option>
	    <option>F6</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Edit variable when variable window is active. You can change only
	      variables with W (as Writable) before variable name. If you are
	      in device selection window, hit tabulator key to move to activate
	      value window.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>F9</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Enter menu.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>F10</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Exit from <command>rts2-mon</command>.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </refsect2>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="variables">
    <title>Variables display</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>Arrays</option>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    For arrays variables, the monitor window shows the following
	    values: mean, size (number of elements), minimum, maximum, median
	    and standard deviation.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    The full content of the array will be displayed when
	    <emphasis>Enter</emphasis> key is pressed while the variable is
	    selected.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="options">
    <title>OPTIONS</title>

    &optiongnu;

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>--command <replaceable>device</replaceable>.<replaceable>command</replaceable></option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Allows user to specify commands to send to connected device(s) once
	    they will become available.  Can be used for example to send
	    reset_next to all connected weather devices.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>-r <replaceable>refresh rate</replaceable></option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Specify refresh rate in seconds. This parameter is usefull if the
	    user wish to limit refreshing of the devices. Defaults to 0.1, e.g.
	    monitor will try to referesh data (and user screen) 10 times per
	    second. Should by used when user wish to limit amount of transmitted data.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>	
        <term><option>-c</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Switch off colors. Usefull for terminals which have problems with colors.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      &clientapplist;
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>SEE ALSO</title>

    <para>
      <citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>rts2</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>,
      <citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>rts2.ini</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>,
      <citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>rts2-horizon</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>
    </para>

  </refsect1>
</refentry>
