<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [

  <!ENTITY dhfirstname "<firstname>Petr</firstname>">
  <!ENTITY dhsurname   "<surname>Kubanek</surname>">
  <!ENTITY dhdate      "<date>2010-10-28</date>">
  <!ENTITY dhsection   "<manvolnum>5</manvolnum>">
  <!ENTITY dhemail     "<email>petr@kubanek.net</email>">
  <!ENTITY dhusername  "Petr Kubanek">
  <!ENTITY dhpackage   "rts2.ini">

  <!ENTITY % rts2 SYSTEM "rts2.ent">
  %rts2;
]>

<refentry>
  <refentryinfo>
    <title>&dhpackage;</title>
    <productname>rts2</productname>
    <productnumber>&rts2version;</productnumber>
    &dhdate;
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        &dhfirstname;
        &dhsurname;
	<contrib>Wrote most of the RTS2 package.</contrib>
	<address>
          &dhemail;
	</address>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <copyright>
      <year>2006 - 2010</year>
      <holder>&dhusername;</holder>
    </copyright>
    &legal;
  </refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>&dhpackage;</refentrytitle>
    &dhsection;
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>&dhpackage;</refname>

    <refpurpose>The configuration file for Remote Telescope System, 2nd version</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>SYNOPSIS</title>

    <para>
      The rts2.ini file is a configuration file for the RTS2. rts2.ini
      contains runtime configuration information for the RTS2 programs. The
      complete description  of  the  file format and possible parameters held
      within are here for reference purposes.
    </para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>FILE FORMAT</title>

    <para>
      The file consists of sections and parameters. A section begins with the
      name of the section in square brackets and continues until the next
      section begins.  Sections contain parameters of the form:
    </para>

    <para>
      name = value
    </para>

    <para>
      The file is line-based - that is, each newline-terminated line represents
      either a comment, a section name or a parameter.
    </para>

    <para>
      Section and parameter names are not case sensitive.
    </para>

    <para>
      Only the first equals sign in a parameter is significant. Whitespace
      before or after the first  equals  sign  is  discarded.  Leading,
      trailing and internal whitespace in section and parameter names is
      irrelevant. Leading and trailing whitespace in a parameter value is
      discarded. Internal whitespace within a parameter value is retained
      verbatim.
    </para>

    <para>
      Any line beginning with a semicolon (``;'') or a hash (``#'') character
      is ignored, as are lines containing only whitespace.
    </para>

    <para>
      The values following the equals sign in parameters are all either a
      string (no quotes needed) or a boolean,  which  may  be  given  as
      yes/no,  0/1 or true/false.  Case is not significant in boolean values,
      but is preserved in string values. Some items such as create modes are
      numeric.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>IMAGE PATH EXPRESSION</title>
    <para>
      Please see
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>rts2</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7</manvolnum></citerefentry>
      for on how image names are formed from expression.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>CONFIGURATION FILE SECTION</title>
    <refsect2>
      <title>database</title>
      <para>Provides configuration values necessary to connect to database.</para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>name</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Database name. Database must be properly configured. Command psql [name] must work for root or user specified with
	    username and password.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>username</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Database username. This user should have write access to important RTS2 tables (observations,..), otherwise
	    RTS2 will not be able to record important values.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>password</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Database password. It is used with username to login to database specified by name.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </refsect2>
    <refsect2>
      <title>observatory</title>
      <para>Provide informations about observatory - its location etc.</para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>altitude</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Observatory altitute in meters. It is recorded to images.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>longitude</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Observatory longitude in degrees. Positive values are east from Greenwich, negative are west - e.g. American
	    locations should have negative longitude, most of European positive.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>latitude</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Observatory latitude in degrees. Positive values are for northern hemisphere locations, negative for southern hemisphere
	    - e.g. Republic of South Africa locations should have negative values, all Europe locations positive.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>ut_offset</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>UT offset in hours (and fraction of hours). If not specified,
	    default to longitude / 15.0. The offset is used for calculation of
	    time dividing two consecutive nights. If current time is after 12 +
	    UT offset, then the night is current local day. If current time is
	    before 12 + UT offset, then the night is preceeding local day.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>min_alt</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Minimum altitude for an object to be selected. Entered in degrees.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>epoch_id</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Epoch id. Epochs are used to divide observatory data to packages which can be easily backed on tapes/DVDs.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>day_horizon</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Sun is below horizon, when its calculated altitude is bellow that value.
              Default to 0 degrees.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>night_horizon</option>
	  </term>
          <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Night starts, when sun gets below that value
              Default to -10 degrees.
	    </para>
          </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>horizon</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Horizon file. This file contains list of horizon
	      hour angle and declination, both in degrees. Horizon is estimated
	      by linear approximation between two sucessive points.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      Horizon points can be given in hour angle and declination
	      (HA-DEC) or azimuth and altitude format (AZ-ALT). For details,
	      please consult
	      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>rts2-horizon</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>
	      man page.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>evening_time</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Evening time - time to cool cameras in seconds. State 1 (evening)
	      starts evening_time seconds before sunset - start of state 2
	      (dusk). Default to 7200 seconds (2 hours).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>morning_time</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Morning time - time to cool off cameras and do calibrations in
	      seconds. State 0 (day) starts morning_time seconds after sunrise,
	      which marks transition from 4 (dawn) to 5 (morning). Default to
	      7200 seconds (2 hours).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>sexadecimals</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Governs writing of RA/DEC to FITS headers. If true, store those
	      values as sexadecimal. Defaults to false.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>base_path</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      String for %b expansion. Expansions characters (%,..) in this string will be ignored. Default to "/images". 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>que_path</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Images are stored on this path before they are processed. Default value is "%b/que/%c/%f".
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>acq_path</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Images are stored on this path for acqusition. Default value is "%b/acqusition/%t/%c/%f".
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>archive_path</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Good images are stored at this location. Those images form the processed image archive.
	      Default value is "%b/archive/%t/%c/object/%f".
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>trash_path</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Bad images are stored at this location. Default value is "%b/trash/%t/%c/%f".
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>flat_path</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Flat images are stored at this location. Default value is "%b/flat/%c/raw/%f".
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>dark_path</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Bad images are stored at this location. Default value is "%b/darks/%c/%f".
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>target_path</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem><para>
	    Location of paths with per-target files. Default is PREFIX directory + 
	    "/etc/rts2/targets". This path holds auxiliary target data -
	    observing constraints, logs, and so on.
	  </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><option>target_constraints_with_name</option></term>
	  <listitem><para>
	    If set to true, path to constraint file will be composed from
	    target name. If false, path will include target id. The path is
	    prefixed with value of <emphasis>target_path</emphasis>, and
	    constraints are held in constraints.xml file. Please see output
	    of
	    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>rts2-targetinfo</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> -ee for details.
	    Defaults to false.
	  </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>nightdir</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Location of night logs; if -, then night logs will not be
	      created. Default to PREFIX "/etc/rts2/nights/%N".
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>model_step_type</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Stepping type for model target. Default value is 2, which will
	      take 2 steps on the net defined in model table. -1 is for linear
	      model, where step is increased by factor of 1, and -2 is for
	      completly random model, which will not make points on the net.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>flat_sun_min</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Flats will be taken when Sun altitude is above this number (e.g.
	      put -7 there if you want to have flats in -7; -5 interval).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>flat_sun_max</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Flats will be taken when Sun altitude is above this number (e.g.
	      put -5 there if you want to have flats in -7; -5 interval).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>telescope_speed</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Telescope speed (in degrees/seconds). Average telescope movement
	      speed.  Should include overhead for ramp up/down times. Typically
	      you will set this to 30-50 % of top telescope speed, depending on
	      how long is the ramp and how much it spend on additional
	      overheads. You can get estimate of average speed by running
	      rts2-nightreport on some full nights - average telescope movement
	      speed is printed with every observation in the output list.
	      Default to 0.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>default_camera</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Deafult camera name. It is used by <citerefentry><refentrytitle>rts2-target</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> 
	      if camera name is not supplied.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><option>logins</option></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Login files for non-DB instances of RTS2. Please check carefuly
	      how RTS2 was build, e.g. if with database support or without it.
	      This value will have effect only if RTS2 was build without
	      database.
	    </para><para>  
	      The file contains : separated login names and passwords. Default
	      is RTS2_PREFIX/etc/rts2/logins.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>  
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><option>header_replace</option></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      String used to replace occurence of the character at odd place
	      with character at even place. For example specifiing "._Aa" will
	      replace all "." with "_" and all "A" with "a". Defaults to empty string.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </refsect2>
    <refsect2>
      <title>centrald</title>
      <para>Centrald information, such as if system should be put to off state each morning, or if it should be "on" after reboot.</para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>logfile</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Logfile for centrald. Can be set to '-' to log to stderr.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>morning_off</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>If set to true, centrald will switch it's state to OFF each morning.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>reboot_on</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      If set to true, centrald will switch it's state to ON
	      after reboot. It's more wise to leave that value to
	      false, as you will then switch the setup on once you
	      will regain connection to the RTS2 computer.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>logfile</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      System logfile. Centrald logs there all system messages. You need to rotate
	      logs, and after rotating them, call killall -1 rts2-centrald. Please see
	      rts2.logrotate for an example how to achieve this with logrotated.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </refsect2>
    <refsect2>
      <title>calibration</title>
        <para>
	  Provides infomations for calibration target - target 6 and Landold (or
	  other) calibration selection.
        </para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>airmass_distance</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
		Maximal airmass distance for calibration targets. This value
		set step size in airmass calibartion table. If set to 0.1,
		airmass calibration table will have steps by 0.1, so targets on
		airmass 1.3 and 1.4 will belong to diferent class and both will
		be considered for observation in calibration target. If both
		targets have airmass between 1.35 and 1.45, only one of them
		will be considered for observation.Defaults to 0.1.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>lunar_dist</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Minimal lunar distance for calibration targets to be considered
	      for selection. It's recorded in degrees, defaults to 20.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>valid_time</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Calibration valid time. If we take at given airmass range image
	      within last valid_time seconds, observing this target is
	      not a high priority.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>max_delay</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Calibration maximal time in seconds. After that time, calibration
	      observation will receive max_bonus bonus. Between
	      valid_time and max_delay, bonus is calculated as: {min_bonus} + (({time from
	      last image}-{valid_time})/({max_delay}-{valid_time}))*({max_bonus}-{min_bonus}).
	      Default to 7200.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>min_bonus</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Calibration minimal bonus. Calibration bonus will not be lower then this value. Default to 1.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>max_bonus</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Calibration maximal bonus. Calibration bonus will not be greater then this value. Default to 300.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </refsect2>
    <refsect2>
      <title>grbd</title>
      <para>Provides values for GRB daemon configuration and GRB observing informations.</para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>port</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Port which will be opened by GRBD either for listening (if server
	      is filled with "-") or which will be contacted on server, if
	      server is filled.  If you have allowed direct connection from the
	      GCN machine (capella.gsfc.nasa.gov), you should put there port
	      number negotiated with GCN. If you do not have direct connection
	      and use some sort of the forwarding mechanism (ussing ssh tunnels
	      or bacofwd), put there number to which port grbd should connect.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>server</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Location of GRB server. "-" when GRBD should open listening
	      connection, or hostname (or IP address) of GRB relaying server.
	      Please see port parameter for futher discussion.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>seplimit</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      If distance for GCN update of GRB position is bellow this value,
	      it is assumed that GRB is still in FOV of the instrument and
	      immediate slew will not be commanded. If distance of telescope is
	      above seplimit, immediate telescope movement will be commanded.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>notvisible</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	       Whenever to record GRBs not visible from current location.
	       Default to true, e.g. all GRBs will be recoreded. If set to
	       false, only GRB with DEC > latitudea - 90 (for nothern
	       hemisphere, e.g. latitude > 0) will be recorded to database.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>  
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>onlyvisibletonight</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Record only GRBs visible tonight from the observatory location.
	      You can check for target visibility using -e and looking for IS
	      VISIBLE TONIGHT. Default to false, e.g. GRBs will be recorded
	      regardless of current visibility.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>add_exe</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Optional executable, which will be passed various parameters about GRB. On command line, this program will receive values (in following order) of
	      tar_id grb_id grb_seqn grb_type grb_ra grb_dec grb_is_grb grb_date grb_errorbox and grb_isnew. Those values are:
	      <variablelist>
	        <varlistentry>
		  <term>
		    <option>tar_id</option>
		  </term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Target ID taken from RTS2 database.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	        <varlistentry>
		  <term>
		    <option>grb_id</option>
		  </term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      GCN GRB target id. Be aware, that different values are
		      ussually assigned by GCN for observations of same GRB
		      with different satellite.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	        <varlistentry>
		  <term>
		    <option>grb_seqn</option>
		  </term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Sequence number assigned from GCN. Please see GCN for details.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	        <varlistentry>
		  <term>
		    <option>grb_type</option>
		  </term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Type number of GCN packet. Please see GCN for details.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	        <varlistentry>
		  <term>
		    <option>grb_ra</option>
		  </term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      J2000 RA of GRB location. In degrees (0-360 range).
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	        <varlistentry>
		  <term>
		    <option>grb_dec</option>
		  </term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      J2000 DEC of GRB location. In degrees (-90 to 90 range).
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	        <varlistentry>
		  <term>
		    <option>grb_errorbox</option>
		  </term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      GRB errorbox. In degrees.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	        <varlistentry>
		  <term>
		    <option>grb_isnew</option>
		  </term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      1 if this is new GRB, 0 if this message is update of an already know GRB.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	      </variablelist>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>know_transients</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      True if GRB marked by GCN are labelled as non-GRB events, e.g.
	      originating from know source variability, should be followed.
	      Defaults to true. This option should be left true while system is
	      in testing phase, as fake grb provide good tests of the system,
	      but once it reach maturity, it is wise to switch know_transients to
	      false.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>validity</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Time for which immediate GRB observing request will be valid.
	      After that time, GRB will be disabled, and its autodisable field
	      will be set to true. If zero, then GRB observing request will
	      never expires, but will be observed governed by GRB merit
	      function. Defaults to 86400 seconds = 1 day. If negative,
	      automatic GRB disabling will not happen, but the event will still
	      be observed with now command issues to executor (if the event is
	      observable when trigger occured).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>gbm_record_above_error</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Whenever FERMI GBM GRBs above error limit will be recorded. If
	      error indicated in GBM message is above gbm_error_limit,
	      depending on this setting, either GBM GRB will be completely
	      ignored (if this is false), or recorded to the database with
	      tar_enabled set to false - e.g. disabled. Default is true, record
	      this value.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>gbm_enabled_above_error</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      If true, FERMI GRBs with error above gbm_error_limit will be
	      recorded as enabled targets. This means that FERMI GRBs will be
	      followed from selector. You most probably do not want this to
	      happen. Default to false.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>gbm_error_limit</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      FERMI GBM GRBs, with error larger then this limit (specified in
	      degrees), will not be followed. According to
	      gbm_record_above_error setting, they will be either ignored at
	      all, or only recorded to the database for reference. Default is
	      15 arcmin = 0.25 of degree.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </refsect2>
    <refsect2>
      <title>swiftfov</title>
        <para>
	  Provides parameters for Swift target - target 10.
        </para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>min_horizon</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Minimal height above horizon for target to be considered.
	      Defaults to 0. A Swift FOV with heigh lover then the min_horizon
	      parameter will not be considered for observation.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>soft_horizon</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Targets with altitude bellow soft_horizon will be assigned
	      altitude of soft_horizon. This is interesting for widefield
	      systems, which would like to follow Swift which center is bellow
	      horizon. Defaults to the "min_horizon" parameter.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </refsect2>
    <refsect2>
      <title>imgproc</title>
      <para>Image processor configuration.</para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>astrometry</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Path for image processing script. Image processing script is
	      called on every obtained image. The only parameter passed to the
	      script is full path of the image.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>imageglob</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Glob pattern (e.g. * are allowed) for images. Those images are
	      processed when system is in day or standby/off state.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>astrometry_timeout</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Timeout for astrometry processing. Astrometry script run time is
	      limited to this number of seconds.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>obsprocess</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Observation processing script. Script is passed ID of observation
	      which shall be processed. Script is run after all observation
	      images were called through astrometry script.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>astrometry_devices</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      List of devices which astrometry results will be feeded back to telescope. Handy if you have multiple devices
	      on a single mount, and would like to base astrometry only on a
	      single device. Default to empty, which means use all devices for
	      astrometry.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>last_processed_jpeg</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Path for last processed image, saved as JPEG. Path can contain %
	      character for expansion. If not defined, the JPEG image will not
	      be created.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>last_good_jpeg</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Path for last good (=with astrometry) image, saved as JPEG. Path
	      can contain % character for expansion. If not defined, the JPEG
	      image will not be created.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>last_trash_jpeg</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Path for last trash (=without astrometry) image, saved as JPEG.
	      Path can contain % character for expansion. If not defined, the
	      JPEG image will not be created.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </refsect2>
    <refsect2>
      <title>selector</title>
      <para>Configuration section for target selector.</para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>night_do_not_consider</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Space separated list of targets types which will not be considered
      for observation during night. Usually you would like to put there flat
      fields - f and F.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </refsect2>
    <refsect2>
      <title>xmlrpcd</title>
      <para>Section for XML-RPC daemon.</para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>page_prefix</option></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Prefix for all pages generated by embedded HTTP server. This is
	      usefull if the server is behind proxy, which maps requests from a
	      given path. For example, if there is proxy server, which maps all
	      requests to /allsky directory to your XML-RPCD HTTP server, set
	      this option to /allsky. Then all generated links will start with
	      /allsky, thus leading to correct adress behind proxy server.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><option>auth_localhost</option></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      If authentification for access is required even from localhost.
	      That apply to all HTTP calls - e.g. both API and Web pages
	      access. If set to false, connection origination from localhost will
	      not require authentification.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      It is reccomanded to leave this option at default, e.g. true. Programs which
	      needs to access XMLRPC or JSON services can specify username and
	      password in configuration file.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><option>images_path</option></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Path for images crated by xmlrpcd. Can contains expansion characters. Default to /tmp.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><option>images_name</option></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Default filename for images created with XMLRPCD. Deafult to xmlrpcd_%c.fits.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </refsect2>
    <refsect2>
      <title>Device configuration</title>
      <para>Device is configured in section which is named by its name. So if
      you have camera called C0 in the system, you must put its configuration
      values to [C0] section in rts2.ini.</para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>script</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Default script for device.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>blocked_by</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Devices which blocks this device. Default is empty - then all
	    devices will block it.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>instrument</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>FITS header entries. Instrument name.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>telescop</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Telescope name.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>origin</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Institution/observer.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>environment</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Space separated list of environmental variables names, which should be recorded to FITS header.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>env_VARIABLE_comment</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>FITS header comment for the environmental variable with name VARIABLE. You can of course specify any name you like.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>after_exposure_cmd</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Command which will be executed by
	    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>rts2-executor</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>
	    directly after exposure. It willl be passed two parameters - first
	    absolute path to file produced, and second arbitary parameter
	    specified with after_exposure_cmd_arg option.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>after_exposure_cmd_timeout</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Timeout for command running after exposure in seconds.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>after_exposure_cmd_arg</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Argument passed to command executed after readout is
	    finished. Please note that first argument is always absolute image
	    filename.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>readout_time</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Camera readout time (in seconds). If set, script length for the
	      camera will include CCD readout time. Default to 0.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>filter_movement</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Filter moving time (in seconds). If set, script length for the
	      camera will include time for moving the filter. In current
	      implementation dump, cannot count filters to move and calculate
	      filter movement time depending on how long filter wheel must move
	      (e.g. how many filters are between target and current filter).
	      Default to 0.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>template</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Template filename. Holds default template for device. Template
	      is used to specify FITS cards which should be created, their value and comment.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <option>no-metadata</option>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Do not write automatic metadata with template. Default to true.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </refsect2>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>SEE ALSO</title>

    <para>
      <citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>rts2</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>,
      <citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>rts2.script</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>
    </para>

  </refsect1>
</refentry>
