<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [

  <!ENTITY dhfirstname "<firstname>Petr</firstname>">
  <!ENTITY dhsurname   "<surname>Kubanek</surname>">
  <!ENTITY dhdate      "<date>2007-05-23</date>">
  <!ENTITY dhsection   "<manvolnum>5</manvolnum>">
  <!ENTITY dhemail     "<email>petr@kubanek.net</email>">
  <!ENTITY dhusername  "Petr Kubanek">
  <!ENTITY dhpackage   "rts2.fitskeys">

  <!ENTITY % rts2 SYSTEM "rts2.ent">
  %rts2;
]>

<refentry>
  <refentryinfo>
    <title>&dhpackage;</title>
    <productname>rts2</productname>
    <productnumber>0.7.0</productnumber>
    &dhdate;
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        &dhfirstname;
        &dhsurname;
	<contrib>Wrote most of the RTS2 package.</contrib>
	<address>
          &dhemail;
	</address>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <copyright>
      <year>2007</year>
      <holder>&dhusername;</holder>
    </copyright>
    &legal;
  </refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>&dhpackage;</refentrytitle>
    &dhsection;
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>&dhpackage;</refname>
    <refpurpose>List of FITS keys written by RTS2 in CCD FITS files.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>SYNOPSIS</title>

    <para>
      RTS2 writes values, which were deemed usefull to record, to FITS
      file. As RTS2 can support various instruments, each with
      different values, the FITS key names cannot be specified with
      FITS template file.

      Instead, various RTS2 devices can define keys which will be
      written to a RTS2 image. 
    </para>

  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>OBSERVATION SPACE AND TIME COORDINATES KEYS</title>
    
    <para>
      RTS2 writes various keys, which describe time and location where the image was taken.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>CTIME</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Computer time, represening number of seconds from 1. Jan 1970.
	    Please be aware, that computer time ingores leap seconds. It should
	    not be used for precise timing analysis.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>USEC</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Nanoseconds (1^10-6 s) of the exposure. Use with CTIME keyword to
	    get precise time of the start of exposure. However pay attention to
	    fact, that it is not precise start time, it is time when executor
	    get message that camera start to take exposure. 
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>JD</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Julian data of exposure start.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>DATE-OBS</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Date of observation in human-readable form. Same as CTIME.USEC or JD.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>EXPOSURE</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Exposure length in seconds and fractions of the second.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>LONG</option>
	  <option>LAT</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Longitude and latitude of the observing site. Longitude is couted
	    positively to east (most of Europe have positive longitude, America
	    have negative), latitude is classic positive for northern
	    hemisphere, counted from the equator.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>ALTI</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Altitude of the observing site in meters above see level.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>IMAGE MANAGEMENT KEYS</title>

    <para>
      Various keys for image management are recored in FITS headers. Those are
      either related to the observation, or to image quality.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>EPOCH_ID</option>
        </term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Epoch of the observation. RTS2 divides images to "epochs", which
	    are time period defined in epoch table.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>OBSID</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Observation ID. This links to observations table, where various
	    details about observation can be found.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>IMGID</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Image ID. OBSID and IMGID is unique key. IMGID is 1 for first image
	    in the observation, 2 for second etc. It does not depends on device
	    - so if the setup has two CCDs, images will be chaotically numbered
	    between those, and you will not find two images with same OBSID and
	    IMGID combination.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>PROC</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Processing bit-mask. Here is the description:
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>SCRIPREP</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Integer value, representing number of loop main script takes. It is
	    0 at beginign, increasign every time script goes to the end of
	    observation.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>SCRIPT</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Script used during observation. That is RTS2 script which device
	    was executing during observation.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>AVERAGE</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Average value (in ADUs) of the image.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>STDEV</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Standard deviation of the image.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>BGSTDEV</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Standard deviation of the image background. Pixels with value
	    higher or lower then 1/10th of the average are not used to compute
	    this value.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>DATE</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Date when the image was written, in standard FITS date string.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>COORDINATES KEYS</title>

    <para>
      Various keys holding all possible coordinates and coordinate corection,
      which play role inside RTS2 system.
    </para>

    <para>
      All values are always recorded as float value in degrees. So right
      ascention is inside 0 to 360 range, declination is in -90 to 90 range.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>RASC</option>
	  <option>DECL</option>
	</term>
	<listitem>
          <para>
	    Right Ascention and DECLination of the image. This is best
	    approximation of the image center location, which included all
	    changes performed by mount, corrections send from feedback
	    astronomy routine and other small changes performed by mount.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    With good enough mount, those values are well suitable for blind
	    mosaicing, calculating offsets only from those coordinates.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>MNT_RA</option>
	  <option>MNT_DEC</option>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    RA and DEC recorded from the mount. Those are mount raw values, the
	    value which mount thinks it is located on. If model for the mount
	    exists, those values are aproximalty target values corrected by
	    model, but with additional noise introduced by back readout frrom
	    mount sensors.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>LAST_RA</option>
	  <option>LAST_DECL</option>
	</term>
	<listitem>
          <para>
	    If present, those are coordinates of last target before we slew to
	    current one. This can be used only to calculate mount slew speed,
	    nothing else.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>TAR_RA</option>
	  <option>TAR_DEC</option>
	</term>
	<listitem>
          <para>
	    Target RA and DEC. This value represent coordinates which were send
	    to the mount. For coordinates readed from the mount see MNT_RA and
	    MNT_DEC, for best image coordinate estimate see RASC and DECL.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>ALT, AZ</option>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Mount altitude and azimuth. This value is either calculated from
	    MNT_RA, MNT_DEC and local time, or raded from mount, if mount
	    support ALT-AZ coordinates.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>MNT_AX0</option>
	  <option>MNT_AX1</option>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Axis sensor values. This number is arbirtary, and depends on mount driver.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>RA_CORR</option>
	  <option>DEC_CORR</option>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Corection in RA and DEC. This is correction computed by RTS2 model,
	    if RTS2 model is enabled. If there was image taken at same location
	      and it gets astrometry, this number represents offset based on
	      astrometry.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>MNT_FLIP</option>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Mount flip. It is most important on standard German equatorial
	    mounts, where rotation angle of the picture depends on which side
	    of meridian it was acquired.
          </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>TARGET KEYS</title>

    <para>
      Following keys are ussually written to target. They represent various target parameters.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>OBJECT</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Target name. It is taken from target database.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>TARGET</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Target ID of the observed target. This ID links to target table,
	    where you can find various target-related informations.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>TARSEL</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Target ID of selected target (target proposed by executor). In
	    chained target (callibrations,..) it might be different from target
	    id of the observed target.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>TARTYPE</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Type of the target. Possible target types are listed in types table.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>MOUNT KEYS</title>

    <para>
      Various mount parameters are recorede. This manual page describes only
      generic values. For mount specific values, please see manual page of the
      mount driver.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>MNT_TYPE</option>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
  	    String describing type of the mount.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>CCD KEYS</title>
    
    <para>
      Various CCD characteristics are recorded. This manul describe only
      generic values, for camera specific one see manul pages for this camera
      driver.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>CCD_NAME</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    RTS2 name of the CDD which acquired the image.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>CCD_TYPE</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Type of the CCD, some string value more or less precisely representing it.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>SEE ALSO</title>

    <para>
      <citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>rts2</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>
    </para>

  </refsect1>
</refentry>
