<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [

  <!ENTITY dhfirstname "<firstname>Petr</firstname>">
  <!ENTITY dhsurname   "<surname>Kubanek</surname>">
  <!ENTITY dhdate      "<date>2011-02-25</date>">
  <!ENTITY dhsection   "<manvolnum>5</manvolnum>">
  <!ENTITY dhemail     "<email>kubanek@fzu.cz</email>">
  <!ENTITY dhusername  "Petr Kubanek">
  <!ENTITY dhpackage   "rts2.queue">

  <!ENTITY % rts2 SYSTEM "rts2.ent">
  %rts2;
]>

<refentry>
  <refentryinfo>
    <title>&dhpackage;</title>
    <productname>rts2</productname>
    <productnumber>&rts2version;</productnumber>
    &dhdate;
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        &dhfirstname;
        &dhsurname;
	<contrib>Wrote this manual page.</contrib>
	<address>
          &dhemail;
	</address>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <copyright>
      <year>2011</year>
      <holder>&fzu;</holder>
    </copyright>
    &legal;
  </refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>&dhpackage;</refentrytitle>
    &dhsection;
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>&dhpackage;</refname>
    <refpurpose>Description of queues available inside RTS2 human scheduling system.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>SYNOPSIS</title>

    <para>
      Queues are used to enable observers interact with what is available for
      the observations. Each queue is a set of targets, which will be scheduled
      by some algorithm. The algorithm for ordering targets to the queue is
      affected by the parameters of the queue, described bellow. 
    </para>

    <para>
      Queue parameterization provides powerfull way how to make sure the
      targets are optionally observed the way observer wants to schedule them,
      and uses all time available during the night. However, some parameters
      are hard to explain in the text - if in doubts, please consult examples
      bellow, they might provide an answer to the question you are asking.
    </para>

  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Queuing mode parameters</title>

    <para>
      Ordering of the targets in the queue is affected by _queing parameter.
      This is so far the most important parameter which describes queue
      behaviour. The parameter can have one of the following values:
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>FIFO</option>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Stands for "first-in, first-out". The targets will be picked from
	    the queue in order they are entered. Targets which are not
	    accesible at the time they should be selected for observations are
	    either skipped and put to the end of queue, or ignored.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>CIRCULAR</option>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    In circular queue, targets are recycled. After the target is
	    observed, it is put to the end of queue. This queue is particularly
	    suited for long-term monitoring, when the goal is to study a long
	    variability of given objects.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>HIGHEST</option>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Will order targets by actual altitute at the observing site. The
	    highest target is then selected for observation.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
	  <option>WESTEAST</option>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Order observations from west towards east. This is the prefered
	    method how to make sure that observations from the set will be
	    observed as close to local meridian as possible.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>Other parameters affecting queue selection algorithm</title>
    <para>
      The following parameters affect target scheduling as well. They are not
      as important as _queing, which determines order of targets in the queue.
      They specify what happens with the target when it is on top of the queue.
    </para>
    <para>
      Those additional parameters might render queue
      <emphasis>inactive</emphasis>. If the queue is inactive, its targets will
      not be selected by the scheduler. Please see
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>rts2-selector</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7</manvolnum></citerefentry>
      for description how the selector handles inactive queues.
    </para>
    <refsect2>
      <title>Time parameters - _start and _end</title>
      <para>
	Those arrays holds time when the observation in the queue should be
	started and end. Both can be empty, start or end filled, or both can be
	filled. The list bellow gives explanation of how the queue is affected
	when various combination is filled.
      </para>
    </refsect2>
    <refsect2>
      <title>Skip targets outside observing limits - -skip_below</title>
      <para>
	This parameter affect what will be done with targets bellow horizon
	when they make it to the top of the queue, and so should be executed.
	The following is possible:
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>Target is in observing limits</term>
	  <para>
	    If the target is in observing limits, the _skip bellow parameter
	    does not affect target scheduling.
	  </para>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term>Target is outside observing limits, _skip_bellow is set to false</term>
	  <para>
	    In such case, the target is simply removed from the queue and the
	    next is evaluated. That applies even to
	    <emphasis>CIRCULAR</emphasis> queue - even for it, the targets are
	    removed once they fall outside observing limits.
	  </para>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Target is outside observing limits, _skip_bellow is set to true</term>
	  <para>
	    In this case, the target will be moved to to the end of the queue.
	    This should enable its observation during later periods. This
	    setting is particularly usefull with <emphasis>CIRCULAR</emphasis>
	    queing, where targets are kept all night for a constatnt
	    monitoring.
	  </para>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </refsect2>
    <refsect2>
      <title>Queue enabled</title>
      <para>
	Determines if the queue will be used during selection. If the queue is
	disabled, its objects will be ignored by the selection algorithm.
      </para>
    </refsect2>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>SEE ALSO</title>

    <para>
      <citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>rts2</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>,
      <citerefentry>
        <refentrytitle>rts2-queue</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
      </citerefentry>
    </para>

  </refsect1>
</refentry>
